<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./IconGene.png" type="Manipulator" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
    <name>CombineScores2Ports</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Combination of gene scores from phenotype, metabotype and genotype analysis (2 input ports)
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        	<b>CombineScores</b> is the last node of <b>PheNoBo</b>.
        	It is the successor of the <b>GeneticNetworkScore</b> node.
        	This node combines 2 results from the phenotype, metabotype and/or genotype analysis.
        	<br/><br/>
        	The aim of CombineScores is to unite 2 sets of gene scores into a single gene score for each gene.
        	The combined scores are used to rank the genes.
        	Genes with a low rank (appearing first in the list of genes) are likely to cause the patient's condition.
        	<br/><br/>
        	CombineScores requires 2 tables with gene scores.
        	For detailed information about the format of the tables have a look at the Input Port section and 
        	at the example files provided at <a href="https://github.com/marie-sophie/mapra">https://github.com/marie-sophie/mapra</a>.
        	<br/><br/>
        	CombineScores calculates 2 different scores.
        	<br/>
        	<b>Combined Gene Score</b>:
        	The combined gene score is a probability calculated from the scores of 2 different, independent analyses
        	yielding scores g<sub>1</sub> and g<sub>2</sub>.
        	The combined score g is determined by using Bayes' formula:
        	g=g<sub>1</sub>g<sub>2</sub>/(g<sub>1</sub>g<sub>2</sub>+(1-g<sub>1</sub>)(1-g<sub>2</sub>)).
        	<br/>
        	<b>Enrichment score</b>:
        	The probabilities are translated into enrichment scores to facilitate the interpretation of the results.
    		The enrichment score of a gene with probability g is determined as log<sub>10</sub>(gn) where n denotes the total number of genes.
    		If the enrichment score is greater than 0, the gene score is higher than expected for a random prediction (where all genes get a score of n<sup>-1</sup>).
    		If the enrichment score is lower than 0, the gene score is lower than expected for a random prediction.
    		<br/>
    		The algorithm of CombineScores is derived from the Phen-Gen tool (see Javed et al., 2014) and is described in more detail at...
    	</intro>
        
        <!--<option name="short name of first option (like in the dialog)">description of first option</option> -->
        
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Gene Scores 1">
        	<b>Gene Scores 1</b>:
        	a table produced by the GeneticNetworkScore node, e.g. from the phenotype analysis.
        	This node uses the columns <b>gene_id</b> and <b>gene_probability</b>.
    	</inPort>
        <inPort index="1" name="Gene Scores 2">
        	<b>Gene Scores 2</b>:
        	a table produced by the GeneticNetworkScore node, e.g. from the metabotype analysis.
        	This node uses the columns <b>gene_id</b> and <b>gene_probability</b>.
    	</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="Combined Scores">
        	<b>Combined Scores</b>:
        	Each row represents a gene and consists of 3 columns: <b>gene_id</b>, <b>gene_probability</b> and <b>enrichment_score</b>.
        	The column gene_probability contains the combined gene scores based on 2 independently calculated sets of gene scores (input port 0 and 1).
        	The gene probability indicates the likelihood that the gene is causal for the patient's disease.
        	The column enrichment_score is a gene score that is normalized for the total number of genes.
        	If the enrichment score is above 0, the gene probability is higher than expected for a random prediction.
        </outPort>
    </ports>    

</knimeNode>
